Guide to the Earle and Thelma Ballou Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Earle and Thelma Ballou Papers
1911-1948
RG 165
Yale University Divinity School Library
8
(21 boxes)
Substantive correspondence, photographs, and slides document the Ballous' life and work in China. Earle and Thelma Ballou were missionaries in Tientsin [now Tianjin], North China, serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions from 1916 to 1948.
Ballou, Earle H. (Earle Hoit), 1892-1987
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Ballou family.
Biographical / Historical
Earle Ballou was born in Saxton's River, Vermont on May 17, 1892. After graduation from Yale College in 1912 he served as Academic Secretary of Dwight Hall, the Yale YMCA for one year and then attended Hartford Theological Seminary. Earle married his hometown friend, Thelma Havens, in March, 1916. Thelma Havens Ballou was born in Chester, Vermont on December 8, 1890. For two years after her graduation from Middlebury College she taught English, history, biology, and German at Springfield High School, Springfield, Vermont, and then attended the Kennedy School of Missions in Hartford for one year.
Earle was ordained as a Congregational minister in June, 1916. The Ballous left for North China in July 1916, where they served under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. Earle and Thelma were stationed in Tientsin (Tianjin) and Peking. Their first son, Hubbard, was born in 1917 and he was later joined by three brothers.
While in China Earle worked closely with the Chinese churches both in Tientsin and as Secretary of the North China Kung Li Hui and the National Christian Council of China. During the Second World War he was detained by the Japanese in Manila until September 1943 when he was repatriated on the Gripsholm. After three years as Executive Secretary for the United Board for Christian Colleges in China, he returned to China, only to be recalled in 1948 to be Acting Secretary for China for the American Board. From 1950 to 1959 he was Executive Secretary of the Congregational Christian Service Committee. He then was called upon by Church World Service to be interim director of a project in Hong Kong for five months and served the National Council of Churches in New York until his retirement in 1961, when the Ballous returned to their hometown, Chester, Vermont.
Earle Ballou died in 1987 and Thelma in 1988. Additional information about their lives and work is available in Thelma Ballou: From the Green Mountains to the Middle Kingdom, a biography published by the Ballou's daughter-in-law Patricia K. Ballou in 1997.
Scope and Contents
This collection is notable for the regular, detailed correspondence of Earle and Thelma to their families in the United States. The same time period, from 1916 through 1940, is documented thoroughly by both Earle and Thelma, offering the opportunity of comparison between their differing views on issues and events. The correspondence is made more valuable by the availability of a biography of Thelma, Thelma Ballou: From the Green Mountains to the Middle Kingdom, by Patricia K. Ballou, which provides information about the Ballous' families and background. The Personal Items and Memorabilia series includes documentation of North China American School, where the Ballou children attended and of Yenching University, which Hubbard Ballou attended. An interesting set of glass slides showing mission activities and other scenes in China completes this collection. Additional materials were donated by the Ballou family in 2011, including correspondence, memorabilia, and the sermons/addresses by Earle Ballou found in Series VI.
The Ballou Papers complement papers of other ABCFM North China missionaries held by the Yale Divinity Library, including those of Hugh Hubbard, Harold Matthews, and Constance Buell.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence of Earle Ballou, 1916-1948
II. Correspondence of Thelma Ballou, 1911-1948
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1916-1997, n.d.
IV. Photographs, 1918-1941
V. Glass Slides, n.d.
VI. Addendum: Sermons/addresses of Earle Ballou, 1938-1976
Missions -- China; Missionaries; Ballou, Earle H. (Earle Hoit), 1892-1987; Ballou, Thelma; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
- Correspondence of Earle Ballou, 1916-1948; Series I
  - EHB to his parents
    - Traveling across the U.S.; descriptions of stops at Yellowstone, Grand Canyon, etc; sailed on RMS Empress of Russia on August 10; stops in Japan; arrival in Peking [now Beijing] September 8, 1916 Jul-Sep (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - From Peking; incl. re. attending language school, work with Chinese students in the Peking College Club; description of a Chinese funeral, 1916 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - From Peking; incl. re. daily life; son Hubbard Walter Ballou born on January 26; Earle teaching Bible class, 1917 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Incl. re. continuing language study; visits with other missionaries; visit to Tientsin [now Tianjin]; visit to Tsing Hua school; summer at Peitaiho resort [Beidaihe], 1917 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Incl. re. political unrest; summer activities; language study; flooding in Tientsin putting their property as risk; move to Tungchou [Tongxian] in September, 1917 Jul-Sep (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Incl. re. awaiting return to Tientsin, which is still flooded; descriptions of flood damage; Earle returns to home and resumes of language study; work with refugees at Christian Union Camp; work at YMCA camp, 1917 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Incl. re. return of Thelma and Hubbard to Tientsin, Earle working at YMCA and language study, 1918 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Incl. re. visit of Earle to outstations with food and aid; making plans for primary schools; meetings held by George Sherwood Eddy result in many conversions of Chinese men; family goes to Peitaiho for summer; Earle attending conferences, 1918 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Incl. re. after return from Peitaiho, Earle teaching English at boys' school in Tientsin, 1918 Jul-Sep (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Incl. ill health, continued work at YMCA and Bible classes; celebration of Armistice; organization of "Congregational Church of Hopei"; mission trip to countryside with Mr. Stanley, 1918 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Incl. re. return to U.S. for four month furlough, 1919 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Incl. re. return to Tientsin in September; student strikes; political unrest; purchase of land for new school; attendance at conference of Interchurch World Movement in Shanghai, 1919 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Incl. re. boycott of Japanese goods; continued student unrest; police opposition to publicity for China for Christ Movement; trip to country outstations, 1920 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Incl. re. daily life; civil war and unrest; move to Peitaiho for summer, 1920 May-Jul (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Incl. re. return to Hopei; contracts for house to be built in Peitaiho; missionary retreat to discuss their work; trips to country churches; shipment of grain and clothing to Chinghai [Qinghai], 1920 Sep-Dec (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Incl. re. routine of mission and relief work; birth of son Laurence Havens Ballou, 1921 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Incl. re. devastation from earthquake in north in December; attendance at Council meeting in Peking; move into new house in Peitaiho; Earle's return to Tientsin; extensive Red Cross road building to facilitate famine relief, 1921 May-Aug (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Incl. re. extended stay in Peitaiho due to Thelma's illness; trips to country outstations; mission compound life, 1921 Sep-Dec (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Incl. re. routine of mission life; civil war threatening, 1922 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Incl. re. Council meeting; civil unrest; soldier activity; conference in Tientsin; vacation in Peitaiho, 1922 May-Aug (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Incl. re. special meetings with Sherwood and Brewer Eddy; extended trip to country; preaching campaign, 1922 Sep-Dec (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Incl. re. planning for furlough; trips to country, 1923 Jan-May (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Incl. re. return from furlough with new son, Robert; now living in Hsiku-E station; Chinese fighting nearby; trips to flooded areas to plan relief, 1924 Aug-Dec (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Incl. re. mission work, meetings, country trip; building new house in Hopei to which they will move, 1925 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Incl. re. District Education Committee meeting in Peking; student riots in Shanghai; country trip, 1925 May-Aug (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Incl. re. fighting nearby; refugees in Hsiku compound, 1925 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Incl. re. family life; refugees; soldier activity; martial law, 1926 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Incl. re. Council meeting; new church built in Hsiku; family to Peitaiho for summer; pirates invade Peitaiho, 1926 May-Aug (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Incl. re. preparation for school opening in new quarters; meetings and social events; son Christopher born Nov. 1, 1926 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Incl. re. foreigners and missionary institutions in danger in central China; Nanking incident; preparations for possible evacuation, 1927 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Incl. re. calming of unrest; family to Peitaiho; retreat and business meetings at Tunghsien, 1927 May-Aug (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Incl. re. family returns to Tientsin; Hubbard goes to Tungchow school; more military unrest, 1927 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Incl. re. attending mission's Annual Meeting in Peking; mention of Eric Liddell; military unrest causing uncertainty, 1928 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Incl. re. War news; discussions re. emergency action; family moved to Concessions for safety; back to Hopei; preparation for school, 1928 May-Aug (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Incl. re. family life; new automobile; Earle on trip to countryside; Christmas celebrations, 1928 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Incl. re. tales of treacherous travel, dust storms, mission life, 1929 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Incl. re. holiday honoring Sun Yat Sen's coffin being transported by train through Tientsin to Nanking, 1929 May-Aug (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Incl. re. government regulation of school ("any attempt to attract students to religion is forbidden"); Chinese church enters on "Five Year Movement" to strengthen and expand the church., 1929 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Incl. re. family illnesses; Eric Liddell preaching at Union Church; gathering of clergy at Russian Club to discuss protests of persecutions in Russia, 1930 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Letters, 1930 May-1934 Apr (Box 4, Folder 41-49)
    - Letters, 1934 May-1936 Dec (Box 5, Folder 50-57)
    - Letters, 1937 Jan-1939 Aug (Box 6, Folder 58-65)
    - Letters, 1940 Aug-1943 Aug (Box 7, Folder 66-70)
  - EHB to Thelma and children
    Scope and Contents
    See also letters of Earle to son Hubbard in Series 2
    - Letters to Thelma and children while on furlough, 1930-1931 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Letter to Thelma regarding plans for departure from China, 1941 Dec; 1932 Feb (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Letters, 1946 Sep-1948 Mar (Box 7, Folder 71-77)
  - EHB to others
    - Circular letters, incl. "Peiping Bulletin" Nos. 15, 22-24; Letter to ABCFM North China Missions re. departure from mission, 1937, 1938, 1941 Nov (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Letters to Mr. Lund, and "Dear Friend"; excerpts of letters, 1947, 1948 (Box 21, Folder 4)
- Correspondence of Thelma Ballou, 1911-1948; Series II
  - To THB from her parents
    - Letters, 1911 Jan-1916 Jun (Box 8, Folder 78-90)
  - From THB to her parents
    - Letters, 1911 Mar-1918 Dec (Box 9, Folder 91-107)
    - Letters, 1919 Jan-1922 Apr (Box 10, Folder 108-125)
    - Letters, 1922 May-1927 Aug (Box 11, Folder 126-149)
    - Letters, 1927 Oct-1935 (Box 12, Folder 150-182)
    - Letters, 1938-1940 (Box 13, Folder 183-184)
  - THB and EHB to son Hubbard
    - Letters to Hubbard while at North China American School, Tungchow, 1931-1934 (Box 21, Folder 5-7)
    - Letters to Hubbard at Yenching University, 1934-1936 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Letters to Hubbard at Yale, 1936-1937 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Circular letters of other missionaries and writings sent as enclosures in letters to Hubbard, 1937-1938 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - THB to/from other family members
    - Laurence (brother), 1911-1916 (Box 13, Folder 185)
    - Misc. (incl. one letter to Earle), 1911-1940 (Box 13, Folder 186)
    - Letters to "Dearest", "Dear Ones All", 1944 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - THB to/from others (non-family)
    - Misc., 1911-1935 (Box 13, Folder 187)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1916-1997,n.d.; Series III
  - Programs, diary, etc. (Box 13, Folder 188)
  - Folder of documents compiled by Henry L. Ballou (Earle's father) re. the Ballous' work in China, including telegrams, memorabilia, Chester, VT church communications, petition of Chinese Christians against Article XIX, Clause 2 of the Draft Constitution for the Republic of China, that "in the State Education the Confucian Doctrine shall be the Basis of Moral Instruction", 1916-1930, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Affidavits listing personal property of Ballous left behind in Peking and Peitaiho, excuted at the U.S. consulate in Shanghai, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - North China American School yearbooks, 1933-1941 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    The 1939 yearbook (Pagoda) has been placed in Record Group No. 209, China American Schools, in order to complete the run of NCAS yearbooks available there.
  - North China American School diploma and report card of Hubbard Ballou; photographs of Principal Lund of NCAS and Hubbard Ballou, NCAS cloth shield (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Yenching University Faculty and Student Directories, 1934-1936 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Yenching University publication: "Yenching Windows" - "published by the class of English 32, Yenching University, Peiping, 1935" (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Yenching University yearbook, 1936 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Yenching University memorabilia: Programs from events: "May Dah Foo Loo - or It Happened at Yen-tsing" (operetta) and "1935 Yenching Revue"; "Freshman Ten Commandments", 1935, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Yenching University Alumni Association directories, 1938-1945 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Anniversary publications of Lu Ho, ABCFM boys' school at Tungchou and Yu Ying, ABCFM boys' school in Peking, 1987, 1990 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Thelma Ballou: From the Green Mountains to the Middle Kingdom, by Patricia K. Ballou; source notes for the book, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Eulogy presented by David M. Stowe at funeral of EHB, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Obituary for THB, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 14)
- Photographs, 1918-1941; Series IV
  - People (Box 13, Folder 189)
  - Peitaiho (Box 13, Folder 190)
  - Tientsin, 1918-1929 (Box 13, Folder 191-192)
  - Peking, 1934 Feb (Box 13, Folder 193)
  - Peking, 1939-1941 (Box 13, Folder 194)
  - Group photo of North China Li Hui Council at annual meeting in Fenchow, Shansi, April, 1937, with key to identify individuals. (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Photograph album of Hubbard Ballou from North China American School (NCAS), 1933 (Box 21, Folder 1)
- Glass slides, n.d.; Series V
  - China (Box 14, Folder 195)
  - China (Box 15, Folder 196)
  - China (Box 16, Folder 197)
  - Egypt and Jerusalem (Box 17, Folder 198)
  - China (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Addendum: Sermons/ addresses of EHB, Series VI
  - Address by EHB at opening convocation of Peiping Union Medical College (PUMC), 1938 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Sermon: "Our Search for God", 1958 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Address to Vermont Congregational Conference: "Who Would Have Thought It?", 1960 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Sermon on 60th anniversary of his ordination:"A Journey Not Alone", 1976 (Box 21, Folder 13)